# 家庭版的一个炒鸡
Home cooking version of stir-fry chicken
# 酱香爆炒鸡
High heat stir fry chicken with soybean paste
# 四民
Si Min.
# 大爷吉祥
Hi Da Ye!
# 师父吉祥
Hi master!
# 今天给我们弄什么好菜啊
What’s the dish we are going to make today?
# 酱香爆炒鸡
High heat stir fry chicken with soybean paste.
# 咱们用的是三黄鸡
What we use is three-yellow chicken.
# 现在鸡的品种很多
Now there are a variety of chicken,
# 有一些土鸡或者麻鸡什么的
like free-range chicken, spotted chicken, etc.
# 但三黄鸡来说
But using three-yellow chicken
# 家庭做比较方便
is more convenient for home cooking,
# 还好熟
also easy to be fully cooked.
# 要用土鸡或者是麻鸡的情况之下
While using free-range chicken or spotted chicken,
# 咱们就用高压锅压一下熟的快
we need to use a pressure cooker to make it done faster.
# 第一步咱们先处理一下
Firstly, we process this chicken.
# 把鸡嘴也叫喙切掉
Cut off the chicken mouth, also called the beak.
# 完了(切掉)鸡爪尖
Then (cut off) chicken feet tips.
# 藏污纳垢
Dirt is hidden there.
# 我给它美美容
Let me make it beautiful.
# 翅尖都得给它去掉
Also cut all wingtips off.
# 这鸡屁股咱们也不要了
Don’t want this chicken butt either.
# 这就干净了
Then it’s clean.
# 一般家庭里来说
Usually for a family,
# 就是买的鸡
chicken is bought from the market.
# 它内脏几乎给扣了
Its viscera are mostly removed.
# 但是扣的不是很干净
But not removed thoroughly.
# 从脊背这儿
From the back,
# 给它开一刀
Slice it open.
# 小四这鸡拾掇得挺干净
Xiao Si cleaned this chicken thoroughly.
# 这样的话一开背之后
After slicing it from the back,
# 咱们就发现一些问题
we found some issues.
# 两边有那血再清洗一遍
There’s blood on both sides. Wash it again.
# 要不省的腥啊
Otherwise, it has a bloody smell.
# 把鸡大卸八块
Chop chicken into pieces.
# 下一步咱们就准备要开始炒制
Next step, we are going to stir fry.
# 这个料我给大家伙简单介绍一下
Let me briefly introduce the ingredients.
# 是两种花椒
Here are two types of Sichuan peppercorn.
# 一种麻椒
One of them is green Sichuan peppercorn.
# 麻椒 花椒
Green Sichuan peppercorn, Sichuan peppercorn,
# 大料 白芷
star anise, baizhi,
# 还有丁香 辣椒
clove, chilli,
# 这边就是葱姜蒜了
then here’s green onion, ginger and garlic.
# 我把这蒜跟葱
I cut garlic and green onion
# 提前切好了一个大段
into sections in advance.
# 这个用的是螺丝椒
This one I chose is screw pepper.
# 螺丝椒它味道比较浓郁
Screw pepper has a stronger flavor.
# 锅烧热之后咱们就下花生油
Heat the pot and add peanut oil.
# 二伯喜欢香油
Er Bai likes sesame oil.
# 香油增香 真的特别鲜
Sesame oil adds a stronger aroma, it’s really tasty.
# 把鸡下到锅里煸炒
Put the chicken into the pot and stir fry it.
# 一共分两次下料白芷不能多放
Add the seasonings in two portions. We should not add too many Baizhi.
# 两片
Two slices.
# 白芷去腥的
Baizhi can cover the odor.
# 大料呢两块
Two pieces of star anise.
# 尤其丁香
Especially clove,
# 一只鸡的话
for a whole chicken,
# 就放这么多 两粒
only add two pieces.
# 麻椒跟花椒呢让它稍微多来一点
In terms of green Sichuan peppercorn and Sichuan peppercorn, we can add a bit more.
# 麻椒稍微多来一点
Add a bit more green Sichuan peppercorn.
# 花椒跟麻椒加上白芷
Sichuan peppercorn with green Sichuan peppercorn, baizhi,
# 还有丁香
and clove,
# 它会出一种更诱人的香味
can bring a tempting aroma.
# 第一步我们先大火煸炒
Firstly, we stir fry it on high heat.
# 把这个水分煸出来
Evaporate the moisture,
# 煸去它一些腥味
to remove some stinky smell.
# 调料就是香味渗透到鸡里边
Let the aroma of seasonings permeate the chicken.
# 这个时候
At this moment,
# 现在锅里还在冒泡时候
we still see bubbling in the pot,
# 证明水气还没有煸干
meaning it’s not dry enough.
# 什么时候小泡没有了
When the small bubbles disappear,
# 它噼里啪啦开始响了
and it starts to produce popping sound,
# 证明水气已经煸的差不多了
it means it’s dry enough.
# 干辣椒为什么先不放
Why don’t you add dried chili pepper first?
# 干辣椒先放的时候它容易糊
If dried chili pepper is added first, it would be easily burnt.
# 出油了开始
The oil is coming out.
# 水气已经差不多快煸干了
The vapor has almost run out.
# 这时候我们再把干辣椒 下里
At this moment, we add dried chili pepper into the pot.
# 下干辣椒的同时
Together with dried chili pepper,
# 我们这时候要下调料
we add condiments into the pot.
# 黄酱
Soybean paste.
# 这是有点像枣庄辣子鸡
This is like making Zao Zhuang chili chicken
# 这时候呢加上酱油
Now add soy sauce.
# 完了这个时候它的颜色不够
The color is not dark enough.
# 我们要拿老抽
We need to use dark soy sauce.
# 老抽呢补点颜色
Dark soy sauce can tone the color.
# 出来到时候是酱红色
When it’s done, it will be dark red.
# 这时候我把姜先拍两下
Now I smash the ginger.
# 来点耗油
Add some oyster sauce.
# 耗油也是增鲜的少来一点
Oyster sauce can also add flavor. Just a little.
# 煸炒完了马上就是烹料酒了
After stir-frying, we add huangjiu rice wine.
# 黄酒
Huangjiu rice wine
# 再次煸炒这时候再开始加水
Stir fry again, then add water.
# 我们加水加到什么时候为合适
How much water is appropriate?
# 就是一没过鸡就可以
Just enough to cover the chicken.
# 热水一没过鸡就合适了
The amount of hot water that can cover the chicken is appropriate.
# 好 颜色红润啊
Good! Nice red color！
# 现在烧一会 可以歇会
Now boil and stew it for a while. We can take a break.
# 大爷 师父
Da Ye, master,
# 现在已经炖到
now it has been stewed
# 我们闻着味儿就来了
We smelled it.
# 15分钟了
for 15 mins.
# 因为三黄鸡还是比较好熟
Because three-yellow chicken is relatively easy to cook.
# 哎呦 这香味出来了
Wow, the aroma comes out.
# 香味扑鼻
Full of fragrance.
# 这时候是先这样
Now it’s like this,
# 第一次味儿入完之后呢
After the first round of toning the flavor,
# 我们把这些姜大料挑出一部分来
we pick some ginger and star anise out of the pot.
# 完了我们进行操作第二波
Then we make the second round of seasoning.
# 这个蒜呢我们是后放
We add garlic in the later round
# 增加它这个蒜的香味
to enhance the garlic aroma.
# 这时候呢再把螺丝椒再倒里头
Now add screw peppers into the pot,
# 增加它辣椒的清香味儿
to add a fresh fragrance from the pepper.
# 这时候我们开大火
Now we turn up the heat on high,
# 收汁 这个汁收到1/3的时候
reduce the sauce. When the sauce reduced to 1/3,
# 我们把这些料捡出来 再把这辣椒放进去
we pick these seasonings out and then put the chili peppers back.
# 螺丝椒的辣味出来之后
After the spicy flavor of the screw peppers comes out,
# 我们再把葱放里头
we add green onions.
# 这样的话它葱也好蒜也好
In this way,  the green onions, garlic,
# 还有螺丝椒也好
and screw peppers
# 不会像以前我们提前炖完以后
will not taste the same way if we stewed for too long.
# 口感和味道可能就比较辣了
The flavor might be too spicy (if we stewed too long).
# 咱们这时候还可以在上面再来一点胡椒
We can then add some pepper powder on top of it.
# 去去腥
To cover the gamey taste.
# 我们就不用加盐了
We don’t need to add salt.
# 之前有这个酱油有耗油
Already having soy sauce, oyster sauce,
# 还有黄酱
and soybean paste,
# 这样咸味就够了
the savour is enough.
# 这时候辣椒味差不多出来了
Now the spicy flavor has almost come out.
# 最后把这个葱放里头
At last, add green onion,
# 再收收汁儿
and concentrate the cause.
# 这时候汤汁已经有点粘稠了
Now the sauce starts to be sticky,
# 颜色也上来了
the color turns dark as well.
# 这个应该是家常版的后放葱 后放蒜
This should be home cooking version, adding green onion and garlic at last,
# 保持葱和大蒜的完整
to keep the shape of green onion and garlic.
# 这蒜稍微还有点嚼头
The garlic is a bit chewy.
# 大爷师父 您看这汁已经粘稠了
Da Ye, master, see, the sauce is sticky.
# 这时候也差不多了我们可以关火
Now is almost the time to turn it off.
# 好
Ok.
# 出锅
Dish it up.
# 家庭版的酱香爆炒鸡
A home cooking version of high heat stir fry chicken with soybean paste.
# 不能给它烧的太干
Cannot make it too dry.
# 鸡头鸡爪 一只整鸡
Chicken head, chicken feet, a complete chicken.
# 好
Good.
# 来着
Here we go.
# 大爷您先来
Da Ye comes first.
# 鸡腿
Chicken leg.
# 看看这个后搁葱什么效果
Let’s see how it is about adding green onion and garlic at last.
# 它还有点艮劲
It’s a bit chewy.
# 好吃么大爷 好吃
How is it, Da Ye? – Delicious!
# 辣味出来了吗
Is it spicy?
# 刚刚好
Just an appropriate level
# 大爷再来点鸡块吧
Da Ye, another piece of chicken?
# 不要了不要了
No need, no need.
# 再来一块吧 不行不行晚上不能吃太多
- Just another piece. – No, no, cannot eat that much at night.
# 回去睡不着了
Cannot fall asleep when get back home.
# 你晚上也睡不着了
You cannot fall asleep at night already.
# 汤都喝了 大爷
You drink the sauce up, Da Ye.
# 葱香 蒜香 酱香
Green onion flavor, garlic flavor, soy paste flavor.
# 应该是叫四椒
Should be counted as four kinds of pepper:
# 有皱皮椒
Screw pepper,
# 有干辣椒 花椒 有麻椒
dried chili pepper, Sichuan pepper, green Sichuan pepper.
# 酱香味浓
Aromatic soybean paste and strong savory.
# 如果要用土鸡
If using free-range chicken,
# 汁上可能会更浓厚
the sauce would be richer.
# 二伯饿了
Er Bai is hungry.
# 一鸡腿一下就下去了
Finish a chicken leg all of a sudden.
# 最主要的什么呀
What’s most special?
# 他这分层次
He sets up multiple layers,
# 下的调料下的非常好
adding seasonings at a very good timing.
# 而且呢
Moreover,
# 还相互不影响 相互不夺味
they are not influenced by each other in the flavour.
# 如果说要先下蒜
If adding the garlic in the beginning,
# 成了蒜籽味了
the dish will be garlic flavour.
# 辣椒和蒜后下整个托出鸡的香味
Adding peppers and garlic later distinguishes the chicken aroma.
# 谢谢 大爷辛苦 师父辛苦
Thanks, Da Ye, master!
# 端出去让大伙尝尝
Bring out to let others have a try.
# 味道不错啊
The taste is good.
# 味道好极了
The taste is great!
# 有网友问您说
There’s a question online that asking you:
# 请问大爷对卤菜有没有研究
Would you have any shared experience on marination, Da Ye?
# 卤水有两种
There are two kinds of brine:
# 一种是白卤
one is white brine,
# 粤菜的这种卤水
Like what Cantonese cuisine uses;
# 但是我们北方
but in north China,
# 实际上它叫酱汤
actually it’s call paste soup.
# 卤汤我建议还是要加糖色
For the brine, I still suggest adding the sugar color.
# 糖色和老抽两样混用
You can replace sugar color with dark soy sauce.
# 这卤水要放什么
What’s the brine made of?
# 比如说桂皮
For example, cinnamon,
# 大料
star anise,
# 花椒
Sichuan peppercorn,
# 香叶
bay leaf,
# 小茴香
fennel seed,
# 砂仁
amomum,
# 豆蔻
cardamom,
# 丁香草果大约在八种左右这种料
clove, tsaoko, around eight these kinds of seasonings.
# 味重的
If it has strong aroma,
# 我们要少放点
we put it less.
# 味儿轻的可以多放一点
If light aroma, we can put it more.
# 然后把这料
Then put all the ingredients
# 放到一个布包里边下锅去煮
into a cloth bag, and boil in the pot.
# 然后加上黄酒
Then add yellow wine,
# 冰糖糖色
sugar color of crystal sugar,
# 适当的加点什么
add a few
# 老抽了
dark soy sauce.
# xh里边有一个冰糖老抽
xh has a crystal sugar dark soy sauce,
# 它的颜色比较稳定
its colour is quite stable.
# 有的时候必要的时候
Sometimes when necessary,
# 可以加一点红曲粉
can also add a bit red yeast rice powder,
# 或者红曲米
or red yeast rice,
# 出来的效果也会好
then the colour effect is also good.
# 然后汤料都准备好了
When soup base is all ready, add
# 葱姜
scallion, ginger,
# 黄酒 盐
yellow wine, salt,
# 包括一些还要放一点酱
also need to put a little paste.
# 然后把原料给它出水
Then boil what you want to marinade in the water,
# 要出干净
remove the dirt thoroughly,
# 煮大约二十分钟
boil for about 20 mins
# 半小时这样
to half an hour.
# 煮好之后
After boiling,
# 所有的沫子都不再出了
until there’s no more offscum coming out.
# 再捞到酱汤里边去卤制
move the ingredient into the brine to marinade.
# 肘子
Pork knuckle,
# 猪蹄大约一个半小时左右就可以了
pork trotters need to boil for one and half hour.
# 像酱牛肉大约得有两个小时
Beef needs about two hours.
# 这酱牛肉出来以后
After beef is done,
# 肘子出来以后
pork knuckle is done,
# 我们不要着急取出来
we cannot hurry to take it out.
# 它在原汤里面要浸泡
It should be soaked in the original soup
# 浸泡两三个小时
for two to three hours.
# 这汤凉了
When the soup cools down,
# 温了能下
becomes warm,
# 能下手了
to touch
# 能下漏勺了
we can use a colander
# 我们再把这原料取出来
to take it out.
# 放在另外一个盘里
Put it in another plate,
# 上边还可以略微的刷一点油
and brush a little oil on the top of it,
# 或者刷一点卤汤
or brush a little master stock
# 这样保持它表面上不会风干
to keep the surface from drying out.